בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is נ"ד. nun daled. We pick up on
נ"ג ע"ב nun gimmel amud bet on the two dots, top of
נ"ג ע"ב, nun gimmel amud bet, a little behind. Okay, and we're
dealing with this question about whether היזק שאינו ניכר שמי היזק. hezek
she'eino nikar shemei hezek. The משנה Mishna said when there's damage that
is not visible, which can exist in a halachic world because it's
worth less because of its halachic status but you can't see it,
you pay if you're intentional, מזיד, Meizid, and not if you're שוגג.
Shogeg. And the question is, the גמרא Gemara is very obviously inclined
from the initial opening to assume that fundamentally you're exempt because it's
not visible and that's just a, you know, and הלכה halacha looks
at an act of damage and not just causing somebody a loss.
And if it's not visible, that would not be considered an act
of damage or the object had and therefore you'd be exempt. But
in order to not allow people this loophole that they can go
ahead and willfully damage somebody else's property, they said that if you're
intentional you have to pay. So the תיקון עולם Tikun Olam is
to make it obligated in the case of מזיד. Meizid. The other
approach, that of חזקיה, Chizkiyah, is to say fundamentally you're obligated, but
they got you off the hook when you're שוגג Shogeg so you
would inform the person. So the גמרא Gemara tries to bring proofs
in both directions
and the weight of all the evidence so far has been that
it's לא שמי היזק, lo shemei hezek, it's not considered to be
damages. Let's take a look now, נ"ג ע"ב, nun gimmel amud bet,
top of the page, about five lines from the top, the two
dots. מתיבי רב פפא. Masvei Rav Pappa. רב פפא Rav Pappa asked,
גזל מטבע ונפסל תרומה ונטמאה חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח. Gazal matbeia venifsul,
terumah venitme'ah, chametz she'avar alav hapesach.
Somebody steals a coin and then the coin has become invalid, like
you stole, I don't know, Confederate money right before the end of
the Civil War. Okay, or somehow the government has announced, you know,
that those coins are no longer valid. So it's not worth anything.
Or תרומה terumah and it became טמא, tamei, which is our case,
or חמץ chametz and פסח Pesach passed over. So it's worthless. Okay,
but this is the object that you stole. And אומר לו, omer
lo, you can say to the person you stole from him, you
stole from, הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha l'fanecha. Look, this is yours,
I'm returning it. You know, it's like that old joke that these,
not exactly, but these guys are on a subway and a guy
comes in and says like, "Okay, everybody give me your wallet." So
guy turns to his friend, "Hey John, you know that 20 bucks
I owe you?"
So it's like, oh, you know, well, here, take your object back,
it's now worthless. So anyway, but the point is is that this
is possible because when you steal, your primary obligation before compensation is
to return the object that you stole, והשיב את הגזילה. v'heshiv et
hagezeilah.
So therefore, since you are returning the object, even though its market
value is now worthless, you have done your obligation of returning the
object. That's the case of הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha l'fanecha. However,
if the object is not just
worthless but actually is damaged, right, if you stole a car and
then you got in an accident, you can't say הרי שלך לפניך
harei shelcha l'fanecha because you're not returning me the object in the
state in which you stole it. So that has to do with
its in the same physical state, so you can say הרי שלך
לפניך, harei shelcha l'fanecha, yes.
Those three cases are actually not the same because
the money that's invalid is truly worthless. The תרומה terumah that's טמא
tamei actually has some use because it can be burned.
And the חמץ שעבר עליו
הפסח
chametz she'avar
alav
hapesach is a Rabbinic decree.
Yes,
that's a good point. So none of them are truly worthless. Well,
the coin isn't worthless, no, because it has precious metal. Oh, that's
true. We're not talking about paper money. Anyway, so okay, that's an
interesting point. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, so let's see how
this is relevant. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואי אמרת
היזק שאינו ניכר שמי היזק, v'ee amart hezek she'eino nikar shemei hezek,
if you say doing a damage if it's not visible you're
liable, האי גזלן הוא ממונא מעליא בעי שלומי. hai gazlan hu mamona
ma'alya bei shlumei. This guy is a
thief and he has to pay full compensation because this object you
wouldn't be able to return this object in this state. So גמרא
Gemara says תיובתא. tiyuvta. So that's a challenge. Now, this is a
very bizarre, as תוספות Tosafos points out, because until now all the
evidence had been from cases about הלכות halachos about damages. This is
not a הלכה halacha of damages. This is a הלכה halacha about
גזלן gazlan and whether you can return the object. So even if
I actually did something actively to the object to now make it
worthless and it's היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar, maybe I have
to pay in הלכות מזיק, hilchos mazik, but who says that in
laws of גזלן gazlan where the primary obligation is to return the
object I can't say הרי שלך לפניך, harei shelcha l'fanecha, the object
is physically in the same state. So תוספות Tosafos says from the
fact that the גמרא Gemara is comparing these two different areas of
הלכה, halacha, it shows you that the question of היזק שאינו ניכר
hezek she'eino nikar is not a local question in laws of מזיק.
mazik. It's
really has to be a more abstract question that can transcend these
two categories. What would that more abstract question be? Do you think
that when something is worth less money but it's not a physical
change, do we consider that to be ניכר? nikar? Do we consider
that to be that the object is different? So if the question
isn't... as a מזיק mazik when it's not visible. I you know,
are you then, that's a very local question to מזיק. mazik. If
the question is more global, when something is worthless, right? Imagine, here's
an example, now maybe it's not the exact same, imagine Confederate money
after the Civil War. Is that well, it's just not ניכר nikkar
the damage. What do you mean it's not ניכר? nikkar? Everything looks
at them and looks and it's like paper money, it's toy money,
it's garbage. Everybody sees that it's garbage. Okay, so what defines something
as being ניכר? nikkar? Now that's a little different because everybody sees
by the context, right? If I see תרומה trumah that's טמא, tamei,
there's nothing for me to be aware, I have to know from
some outside information about what happened to this. But anyway, תוספות Tosafot
says that's the question. The question is, is when it's when it's
not physical, could we still consider it to be that the object
is different? Because it's worthless, is the object different? If you want
to say maybe that's a better way, not is it ניכר, nikkar,
but is it different? So if it's different, I would have to
pay as a מזיק, mazik, and if it's different, I wouldn't be
able to say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. The fact that
a גזלן gazlan can say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha proves
that we don't consider the object different, and therefore you're not going
to pay as a מזיק. mazik. Okay, so that's a very strange,
again, that the גמרא Gemara brings a proof from the laws of
גזלן. gazlan. So תוספות Tosafot says what that really shows is the
question isn't just a local question about מזיק, mazik, it's a question
of when it's worthless, do we consider it to be a different
type of an object? A changed object? And the answer from this
is we don't, and therefore the גמרא Gemara says we should assume
that a מזיק mazik does not have to pay. Okay, so that's
at least how we have proven it, but now we're going to
say maybe it's really a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. The גמרא Gemara
says לימא כתנאי. leima ketannai. Let's see if this is a debate
of תנאים Tannaim of היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she-eino nikkar. המטמא והמדמע
והמנסך אחד שוגג ואחד מזיד חייב דברי רבי מאיר.
ha-metamei ve-ha-medamea ve-ha-menasech echad
shogeg ve-echad mezid chayav divrei Rabbi Meir.
So
if again these are the cases in the משנה, Mishnah, you cause
טומאה tumah to תרומה trumah let's say, you mix up תרומה trumah
and חולין, chullin, or you pour יין נסך, yayin nesech, שוגג או
מזיד חייב דברי רבי מאיר. shogeg o mezid chayav divrei Rabbi Meir.
So this is not an opinion quoted in the משנה. Mishnah. This
says you're חייב chayav even by שוגג. shogeg. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi
Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who's apparently who's the author of
our משנה, Mishnah, says בשוגג פטור במזיד חייב. be-shogeg patur be-mezid chayav.
You know, you're פטור patur by שוגג, shogeg, you're חייב chayav in
the case of מזיד. mezid. That's our משנה. Mishnah. So מאי לאו
בקמיפלגי? mai lav bik-miflagi? So let's understand what is the debate about
whether you should pay when you're שוגג shogeg or not. Maybe it's
this debate. דמר סבר היזק שאינו ניכר שמי היזק. de-mar savar hezek
she-eino nikkar shmei hezek. One says fundamentally you're exempt, and if fundamentally
you're exempt the only case we'll make you pay is מזיד, mezid,
right, because then we have to stop willful damaging, but fundamentally you're
פטור. patur. ומר סבר u-mar savar and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
says even a שוגג shogeg pays would be of the opinion of
I'm sorry, did I skip it? I'm sorry, I started the wrong
way. מר סבר mar savar רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds היזק שאינו
ניכר שמי היזק, hezek she-eino nikkar shmei hezek, then it's considered to
be real damages, and since it's real damages you would pay even
in a case of שוגג. shogeg. ומר סבר u-mar savar and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds לא שמי היזק, lo shmei hezek, it's not
real damages, and therefore you fundamentally should be פטור patur in both
cases, but we'll have to make a מזיק mazik pay. Okay, so
if you're going to pay whether שוגג shogeg or מזיד, mezid, presumably
that's because in principle you fundamentally are obligated, so we're not going
to make any distinctions. If you're only paying in a case of
מזיד, mezid, it would be because fundamentally you are פטור. patur. Okay,
so that seems to be a pretty reasonable explanation. So אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, no, not necessarily. דכולי
עלמא היזק שאינו ניכר לא שמי היזק. de-chulei alma hezek she-eino nikkar
lo shmei hezek. We could say everybody says it doesn't constitute damages.
And again, that's clearly where all the evidence is pointing towards. והכא,
ve-hacha, so if that's true, if you're fundamentally פטור, patur, why would
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir make you pay in a case of שוגג?
shogeg? והכא בקנסו שוגג אטו מזיד קמיפלגי. ve-hacha bik-nasu shogeg atu mezid
kamiflagi. The debate is if we're going to make a מזיד mezid
pay, do we have to make a שוגג shogeg pay as well?
Okay, now why should we do that? Well, I mean one reason
could just be like, you know, like לא פלוג, lo plug, like
to make it seem like it's real, you know, more a matter
of law, so we're just going to do it across the board
and it feels like and becomes like it's communicated as a more
weightier type of a thing. But the other reason is, is because
if we don't, how can you always prove whether a guy's שוגג
shogeg or מזיד? mezid? Right? Then we're going to always have to
try and somebody who was מזיד mezid could make it look like
he was שוגג. shogeg. Whoops! So anyway, so it's easier to just
say everybody has to pay. Okay, and look, let's face it anyway,
the guy, even the guy who's שוגג, shogeg, you know, he did
cause damage to this other person, and maybe you have to be
a little bit you maybe have to fine him as well because
he should have been less negligent. So that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
approach. רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir approach is we're going to make everybody
pay שוגג shogeg and
מזיד. mezid. דמר סבר קנסו שוגג אטו מזיד. de-mar savar knasu shogeg
atu mezid. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says yeah, in principle you're פטור
patur in both cases. You know, you shouldn't pay at all, but
since we're going to make the מזיד mezid pay, we're also going
to make the שוגג shogeg pay. But all of that is a
קנס. knas. ומר סבר לא קנסו שוגג אטו מזיד. u-mar savar lo
knasu shogeg atu mezid. No, they didn't, you know, they didn't expand
it, they only made the מזיד mezid pay, not the שוגג. shogeg.
But everybody agrees it's a קנס. knas. The question is how narrow
or how broad. Okay, so now we have a debate of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda where רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir makes a קנס knas across the board, שוגג shogeg and מזיד,
mezid, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda just makes it in a case
of מזיד. mezid. So now what we're going to look at for
most of the remainder of the דף daf is to try to
line up all the debates of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in all different cases in ש"ס Shas about whether
we fine a person in a case of מזיד. mezid. or even
cases of שוגג. shogeg. And the problem is that it's not going
to make sense. They're going to seem to switch sides regularly, whether
we קונס, kones, whether we fine
in the case of שוגג shogeg or not, and the גמרא's Gemara
going to try to make some order and some sense of their
different positions. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: ורמי, varami, where am I? ורמי, varami, ורמי דרבי מאיר
אדרבי מאיר ורמי דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה. varami de-Rebbe Meir a-de-Rebbe Meir
ve-remi de-Rebbe Yehuda a-de-Rebbe Yehuda.
We're going to show a ברייתא brayta that shows that רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda both seem to switch sides.
Okay, דתניא, de-tanya, we learned in a ברייתא. brayta. המבשל בשבת, ha-mevashel
be-Shabbat,
somebody cooks on שבת, Shabbat, can you eat from the food? So
בשוגג יאכל, be-shogeg yokhal, if he did it accidentally, he can eat
from it. All right, so therefore there's no קנס knas by שוגג,
shogeg, we didn't fine him. במזיד, be-meizid, if he did it willfully,
לא יאכל, lo yokhal, he can't eat, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rebbe
Meir. So this has רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir saying
you're only going to fine the מזיד, meizid, not the שוגג, shogeg,
right? The exact opposite of what he said before. Not the opposite,
but you know what I mean, in terms of the שוגג, shogeg,
it's the opposite position. He's not going to fine the שוגג. shogeg.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbe Yehuda omer, and now we're going to find
that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is going to fine the guy who's
שוגג. shogeg. רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbe Yehuda omer, בשוגג יאכל למוצאי שבת.
be-shogeg yokhal le-motza'ei Shabbat. If you did it unintentionally, you can't eat
on שבת Shabbat itself. You can eat on מוצאי שבת, motza'ei Shabbat,
but you can't benefit from it on שבת Shabbat itself. במזיד, be-meizid,
if you did it willfully, לא יאכל לעולם, lo yokhal le-olam, you
can never eat forever.
Now, so he's not fining the שוגג shogeg to the same extent
as the מזיד, meizid, but nevertheless he is imposing, he is fining
the שוגג shogeg guy. So there they switch sides. And then we
have רבי יוחנן הסנדלר אומר, Rebbe Yochanan HaSandlar omer, רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan the sandal maker, the shoemaker: בשוגג יאכל למוצאי שבת, be-shogeg yokhal
le-motza'ei Shabbat, okay, if it was accidental, you can eat after שבת,
Shabbat, לכם ולא לו, lakhem ve-lo lo, other people can eat the
food after שבת Shabbat if it was for שוגג, shogeg, okay, but
you can't because you presumably cannot be the beneficiary of your own
חילול שבת. khillul Shabbat. And במזיד, be-meizid, if you did it willfully,
לא יאכל לעולם לא לו ולא לאחרים, lo yokhal le-olam lo lo
ve-lo le-akherim, nobody can eat from it, not you and not anybody
else forever. And this the גמרא Gemara says he's coming from another
גמרא Gemara says, he's coming from a דאורייתא de-oraita perspective, that he
thinks that from the תורה Torah perspective, if you violate שבת Shabbat
willfully, that that makes any product of it fundamentally forbidden. It's not
a fine, it's like the product of a violation of חילול שבת
khillul Shabbat by nature has to be off-limits. Okay, but that's רבי
יוחנן הסנדלר, Rebbe Yochanan HaSandlar, that's not our interest right now. Anyway,
here you see that רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and it might be
helpful to start to make a chart because if
you basically have, you've got רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda and you're going to have all these different cases. So
you're
going to have the case of, so we had the case about
היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she-eino nikar.
Okay, so this is whether you fine the case of שוגג. shogeg.
So רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir yes did a שוגג shogeg and רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda did not do a שוגג. shogeg. This is all
about the שוגג. shogeg. And then we have שבת, Shabbat, חילול שבת,
khillul Shabbat, where רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir did not fine the שוגג
shogeg and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda did fine the guy who was
a שוגג. shogeg. Okay, so they're switching sides. Okay, it's going to
keep on going all the switching sides. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says: קשיא דרבי מאיר אדרבי מאיר קשיא דרבי
יהודה אדרבי יהודה. kashya de-Rebbe Meir a-de-Rebbe Meir, kashya de-Rebbe Yehuda a-de-Rebbe
Yehuda.
So they're switching their position. דרבי מאיר אדרבי מאיר לא קשיא. de-Rebbe
Meir a-de-Rebbe Meir lo kashya. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir on himself is
not a problem. Why not? כי קניס בדרבנן בדאורייתא לא קניס. ki
kanis bi-drabbanan, be-de-oraita lo kanis.
So if you take a look, רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, this is
a דאורייתא de-oraita violation. Damaging somebody's property, it is a דאורייתא de-oraita
violation, you can't damage someone's property, but technically it wasn't really
damaged, so I didn't technically do a תורה Torah violation in the
act. So since here it was a תורה Torah violation, now you
should say, wait a minute, if it's a תורה Torah violation, you
should be stricter, you should be more willing to punish. No, but
the point is if it's a תורה Torah violation, then people are
going to just be much more careful anyway. I don't need the
rabbis to fine. This is going to happen a lot less frequently.
This is דאורייתא. de-oraita. This is דרבנן, de-rabbanan, people are going to,
there's a much more of a slippery slope, people are not going
to be, people are going to be more lax. Here I'm going
to have to make the fine, I'm going to have to be
stricter by דרבנן. de-rabbanan. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: כי קניס
בדרבנן בדאורייתא לא קניס. ki kanis bi-drabbanan, be-de-oraita lo kanis. והמנסך דאורייתא
הוא וקא קניס? ve-ha-menasekh de-oraita hu ve-ka kanis? What do you mean?
One of the cases in the משנה Mishna was pouring wine to
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. That's a תורה Torah violation. So the גמרא
Gemara says: no, משום חומרא דעבודה זרה קניס ליה. mishum khumra de-avoda
zara kanis lei. Okay, no, that's because it's like the flip. If
you did something so terrible that you were מנסך menasekh to עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, then, I mean חילול שבת khillul Shabbat is also
pretty darn bad, but עבודה זרה avoda zara is like the worst.
So that case we are going to fine you. Okay, but basically
the basic answer is other than saying that עבודה זרה avoda zara
is so terrible, the basic answer is if it's worse, we're not
going to fine you, if it's not as bad, that's more of
a need for fining you. Okay, let's take a look. That's רבי
מאיר. Rebbe Meir. And now we're going to say the exact opposite
for רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. Which is the thing that for you
is the important factor for fining or not fining might be the
reverse based
on... Okay, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אדרבי יהודה aderabbi Yehuda לא
קשיא. lo kashya. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not a
problem. כי לא קניס Ki lo kanis בדרבנן bederabbanan דאורייתא קניס, deoraita
kanis, the exact reverse. He doesn't fine you by Rabbinic because what
you did wasn't so bad. And but if you violated שבת, Shabbat,
he is going to fine you. That's pretty bad. Okay. So whether
you're more strict or less strict by a biblical violation, that's the
reverse. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ותמנא נסך דאורייתא ולא
קניס. ve-tam-na-sech de-oraita velo kanis. One minute, but here you had you
also had pouring wine to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. That's biblical. That's
a very weighty biblical obligation. So why isn't he fining you? So
the same reason but now again reverse. משום חומרא דעבודת כוכבים מיבדל
בדילי מינה. mishum humra de-avodat kokhavim mivdal badle minei. No, because עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah is so terrible that I don't have to fine
people because they're not going to do it anyway. Okay? So it's
a very ironic, right? So things that are worse, is that more
of a reason to fine or more of a reason not to
fine? But we're using that as explaining how they're reversing their positions.
And worshipping עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is you're חייב מיתה בבית דין?
hayav mita be-veit din? Yeah, yeah, which is the same as
שבת.
Shabbat. Yeah, but it's more theologically severe. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Now we're not done though. We're going to have
to have more things to line
up. ורמי דרבי מאיר אדרבי מאיר בדאורייתא. verami de-Rabbi Meir ade-Rabbi Meir
be-de-oraita. One minute, you're telling me that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir here,
right? So now we're saying that the key is the explanation is
that this is דרבנן derabbanan fundamentally and this is דאורייתא. deoraita. And
that's how they're debating. So now so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir for
a דאורייתא deoraita you're saying does not fine by a case of
שוגג. shogeg. Okay, one minute. I'm going to show you in a
case of דאורייתא deoraita he does fine in a case of שוגג.
shogeg. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in a ברייתא: Braisa: הנוטע בשבת בשוגג
יקיים
במזיד יעקר. hanotea beshabat beshogeg yekayem bemeizid yeaker. If you plant on
שבת, Shabbat, if it's שוגג, shogeg, you don't have to uproot it.
If it's on מזיד, meizid, you have to uproot it. So so
far that's exactly consistent with רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. He does not
fine in a case of שוגג shogeg by a דאורייתא. deoraita. ובשביעית,
Uvshvi'it, but on שביעית, Shvi'it, בין בשוגג בין במזיד יעקר דברי רבי
מאיר. bein beshogeg bein bemeizid yeaker divrei Rabbi Meir. Even in case
of a שוגג shogeg you have to uproot it. So there's a
case that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is strict by a דאורייתא deoraita
by שוגג. shogeg. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer: בשביעית בשוגג יקיים
במזיד יעקר. beshvi'it beshogeg yekayem bemeizid yeaker. No, no, no. He says
by שביעית Shvi'it you don't have to uproot it on שוגג. shogeg.
בשבת בין בשוגג בין במזיד יעקר. beshabat bein beshogeg bein bemeizid yeaker.
But on שבת Shabbat by שוגג shogeg you do have to uproot
it. So again they're reversing themselves. Okay, so it's all getting very
confusing. But let's basically if you first focus on the דאורייתא, deoraita,
right, they're consistent because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says on שבת, Shabbat,
right, if you look at it, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says on
שבת Shabbat you don't have to uproot it in a case of
שוגג, shogeg, הנוטע בשבת בשוגג יקיים, hanotea beshabat beshogeg yekayem, which is
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says by שבת. Shabbat. And רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says בשבת בין בשוגג בין במזיד יעקר. beshabat bein beshogeg
bein bemeizid yeaker. Okay, so they're consistent, right, with what they say
by שבת. Shabbat. Okay.
But now they have reversed themselves by שביעית. Shvi'it. And you can't
say that the issue is דאורייתא deoraita because שביעית Shvi'it is presumed
to be also דאורייתא. deoraita. Now it's interesting because you could have
said שביעית Shvi'it nowadays is דרבנן. derabbanan. Okay. And it's funny that
the גמרא Gemara doesn't go there. But they said exactly what they've
been saying by שבת, Shabbat, okay, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't
fine שוגג shogeg and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does. But by שביעית
Shvi'it they reverse themselves. So why are they reversing themselves by שביעית?
Shvi'it? So the גמרא Gemara
says, ולטעמיך, uleteimeich, the גמרא Gemara says, why are you showing this
as a contradiction from one רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in one case
to another רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? תיקשה לך היא גופא. tikshe lach
hi gufa. The question emerges from this very
ברייתא Braisa itself. מכדי הא דאורייתא והא דאורייתא. mikhdi ha de-oraita ve-ha
de-oraita. שבת Shabbat and שביעית Shvi'it are both דאורייתא. deoraita. מאי שנא
שבת ומאי שנא שביעית. mai shna shabbat u-mai shna shvi-it. Why did
you do it, why by שבת Shabbat do they hold one way
and by שביעית Shvi'it they hold the mirror opposite? אלא התם כדקתני
טעמיה. ella hatam kid-katani taamei. If you want to know why רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is strict by שביעית Shvi'it even though it's a
דאורייתא, deoraita, here's the reason. אמר רבי מאיר מפני מה אני אומר.
amar Rabbi Meir mipnei ma ani omer. We got a ברייתא, Braisa,
he explains himself. Why am I saying בשבת בשוגג יקיים במזיד יעקר?
beshabat beshogeg yekayem bemeizid yeaker? By שבת Shabbat by שוגג shogeg I'm
not going to fine the guy. ובשביעית בין בשוגג בין במזיד יעקר.
uvshvi'it bein beshogeg bein bemeizid yeaker. But by שביעית Shvi'it I'm going
to make him uproot it even by a case of
שוגג. shogeg. מפני שישראל מונין לשביעית ואין מונין לשבתות. mipnei she-yisrael monin
li-shvi-it ve-ein monin le-shabatot. Because we count years based on שביעית Shvi'it
and we don't count things based on שבתות. shabatot. What does that
mean? It basically means that here I am, I see you eating
ערלה. orlah. This is the example רש"י Rashi has. I see you
eating from a tree I know you planted a few years ago.
Okay, so if you planted it only a few years ago, it
must be that it's out of the ערלה orlah period. So I'm
going to do the math in my head, right? It's like unfortunately
some people do when somebody has a baby pretty soon after a
wedding, they do the math in their head. So I'm going to
do the math in my head, and I'm doing the math in
my head and I'm saying like, oh wait a minute, that means
that it was planted on שביעית. Shvi'it. If this year is already
the fourth year, right, then I know that it must have been
planted on שביעית. Shvi'it. So that must mean that it's מותר muttar
to plant on שביעית, Shvi'it, right? So therefore it's going to be
obvious to everybody that this was planted on שביעית Shvi'it because they'll
see you eating from it four years, you know, four years later.
So in hindsight it'll be obvious to everybody it was planted on
שביעית. Shvi'it. So that will be like a violation of the sanctity
of שביעית, Shvi'it, you know, that we let we let it happen
and we let it be a public matter and we don't and
so on. So therefore we're going to fine you. force you to
uproot it. Okay, but by שבת, Shabbos, how are people going to
know whether you planted it on a שבת Shabbos or on a
weekday, right? How's that going to be known to anyone? So we
don't have to force you to uproot it. So I'm going to
be more מחמיר machmir by שמיטה Shmita because I just don't want
it to be visible to people that שמיטה Shmita was violated. That's
why. It's not so much of a fine. דבר אחר, Davar acher,
here's another explanation. נחשדו ישראל על השביעית ולא נחשדו על השבתות. Necheshdu
Yisrael al hashevi'is velo necheshdu al hashabatos. Okay,
which is maybe a more straightforward in terms of along the lines
of what we've been talking about before. Why is Rabbi Meir more
lenient and does not fine in the case of a דאורייתא? de'oraisa?
Because the Torah restriction does enough to control the behavior. But by
שמיטה, Shmita, there was a lot of laxity around שמיטה Shmita observance
and even though it was a דאורייתא, de'oraisa, because there was laxity
around it, there was a particular need to do it by שמיטה.
Shmita. Okay, so that's why he did it by שמיטה. Shmita. Okay.
מאי דבר אחר? Mai davar acher?
Why do you need another reason? הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, here's what
it's saying. וכי תימא שבת נמי זימנין דמיקלע יום שלושים בשבת. Vechay
teima Shabbos nami zimnin demikla yom sheloshim beShabbos.
Sometimes by שבת, Shabbos, people will do the math and figure out
it was planted on שבת. Shabbos. How is it? Because if something
was planted thirty days before the beginning of a new year of
a like, you know, of a שמיטה Shmita year or anyway of
a new year, then that counts like it already has one year
to it to its growth, right? In terms of the ערלה. orlah.
Right? It's not like it's a year measured on 365 or 354
days from the day it's planted. It goes by what year in
the cycle it was planted. So if somebody planted a month before
the end of the year and that day was שבת, Shabbos, so
I'm going to do the math and I'm going to say, wait,
wait, wait, how are you eating now? It's only year four, oh
it's only year three, oh it's year four because you planted it
right before the end of the year. Oh wait a minute, that
would have been שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so sometimes you'll do that math.
דמיקלע יום שלושים בשבת, Demikla yom sheloshim beShabbos, דניחא ההוא יומא דסליקא
ליה שתא. denicha hahu yoma desalika lei shata. Only if you were
to plant it on שבת Shabbos would you have gotten in the
thirty days before the end of the year. ואי לא לא סליקא
ליה שתא. Ve'i lo lo salika lei shata. If not, not. So
because there's a concern that people will, that also, you know, that
doesn't fully explain the difference between שמיטה Shmita and שבת. Shabbos. So
תא שמע דבר אחר, Ta shema davar acher, the real difference is
נחשדו ישראל על השביעית ולא נחשדו על השבתות. Necheshdu Yisrael al hashevi'is
velo necheshdu al hashabatos. Okay, so that the people are more lax
by שמיטה. Shmita. So because they're more lax we have to therefore
make a קנס. knas. So Rabbi Meir in his case of דרבנן
derabbanan for Rabbi Meir, when he makes a fine, what we're going
to add to this is a case of שמיטה, Shmita, which even
though it is דאורייתא, de'oraisa, but it's a דאורייתא de'oraisa that people
are lax in. And since they're lax in a דאורייתא, de'oraisa, it's
like a דרבנן derabbanan and he's going to make a fine in
the case of שוגג. shogeg. Okay, now we have to work out
Rabbi Yehuda because Rabbi Yehuda also reverses his position. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay,
דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה לא קשיא. deRabbi Yehuda aRabbi Yehuda lo kashya.
Now how is Rabbi Yehuda not a problem? Rabbi Yehuda normally does
do it by a שוגג shogeg by שבת, Shabbos, but by שמיטה
Shmita he doesn't fine by שוגג. shogeg. Why is שמיטה Shmita different?
So the גמרא Gemara says, באתריה דרבי יהודה חמרו להו שביעית. Be'asrei
deRabbi Yehuda chamru lehu shevi'is. No, in Rabbi Yehuda's place שביעית Shevi'is
was so strict he didn't need to make the fine by case
of שוגג. shogeg. How do we know it was so strict? דההוא
דאמר ליה לחבריה, Dehahu de'amar lei lechaveriah, a certain man said to
his friend, דייר בר דיירתא, Dayyar bar dayarta,
which basically means convert the son of a convert, which is not
so nice, you're not supposed to like, you know, whatever, whatever with
אונאת דברים, ona'as devarim, I don't know. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei,
so anyway he called him a name. Okay, he called him something
in order to put him down. So he said back to him,
yo, what, you think you're so special because you were born Jew?
אנא לא אכלי פירא דשביעיתא כוותך. Ana lo achali peira deshevi'as kavach.
I don't eat שמיטה Shmita food like you do. So you know,
big deal, like I'm more observant than you are. So anyway, okay,
so it's fascinating. But I have to tell you, I don't begin
to understand this גמרא. Gemara. So because he was pointing out and
calling the guy on the fact that he ate שמיטה Shmita food,
that proves that שביעית Shevi'is is very חמור? chamur? If anything you
would prove that שביעית Shevi'is is קל, kal, that people are violating
it. Oh, but you're called out on it. Okay. Anyway, I don't
have, I don't see anywhere from this story that we see that
שביעית Shevi'is is so חמור. chamur. Number one. Number two, let's not
forget that Rabbi Yehuda by דאורייתא de'oraisa even by something like שבת,
Shabbos, right? Even something like שבת Shabbos which we assume is not
only דאורייתא de'oraisa but very weighty, he feels a need to make
a fine, right? So I don't get why if you need to
make a fine by שוגג shogeg by שבת Shabbos why you don't
have to do it by שביעית. Shevi'is. I really, I don't really
understand the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer. Okay, but anyway we're going to move
on. Okay, תא שמע, Ta shema, let's have another
case. אכל תרומה טמאה משלם חולין טהורים. Achal terumah temei'ah meshalem chullin
tehorim. Now the הלכה halacha is, is that if you eat תרומה,
terumah, if you eat a תרומה terumah of a כהן kohen במזיד,
bemayzid, then you're like a מזיק mazik and you just pay back
how much it was cost. But if you eat it בשוגג, beshogeg,
accidentally, it's a very strange הלכה, halacha, which is what you do
is you pay the guy back in food, and that food when
you pay him back becomes תרומה terumah in that act of paying
back. There's actually a debate in the גמרא Gemara which is if
I stole a bushel from you and now it's בשוגג, beshogeg, not
stole, I ate a bushel of yours בשוגג. beshogeg. Do I pay
you back a bushel or in food, or do I pay you
back its value in food? Like you go how much do you
sort of really still look at it in terms of dollars and
cents since now we're focusing also on the object and the object
is becoming תרומה. Terumah. But anyway, so here's the case is
that you ate תרומה טמאה. Terumah temeiah. Now, you ate תרומה טמאה,
Terumah temeiah, so its actual value is less because it's תרומה טמאה
Terumah temeiah it doesn't have that much value. But nevertheless, I mean
you have to pay back food and we want you to pay
back טהור tahor food because then it'll become תרומה טהורה Terumah tehorah
for the כהן. Kohen. It'll be as long as you're paying back,
you might as well pay back טהור tahor food. You're paying back
טהור חולין, tahor chullin, not תרומה, Terumah, but in the act of
paying it back to the כהן Kohen it becomes תרומה. Terumah. So
you might as well pay him back טהור tahor one so he'll
be better off. Now if you're paying back the same
quantity, he actually
gets more money back than he lost. Even if you're paying him
back equal to the value, nevertheless people would rather have less תרומה
טהורה Terumah tehorah than more תרומה טמאה. Terumah temeiah. So we're going
to ask you to pay back טהור tahor food. You're paying back
טהור חולין tahor chullin and it's going to become תרומה טהורה Terumah
tehorah even though what you ate was תרומה טמאה. Terumah temeiah. Is
that clear? Yeah? Okay. So אכל תרומה טמאה, achal Terumah temeiah, you
ate תרומה טמאה, Terumah temeiah, משלם חולין טהורים. meshaleim chullin tehorim. You
should pay back טהור חולין. tahor chullin. שילם חולין טמאים shileim chullin
temein if בדיעבד bedieved you gave back חולין טמאים chullin temein and
then in the process of paying it back it became תרומה טמאה.
Terumah temeiah. So effectively you're giving back the exact same thing that
you ate. Okay. So מהו, mahu, what's the
הלכה? halacha? אמר סומכוס משום רבי מאיר, amar Sumchus mishum Rabbi Meir,
בשוגג beshogaig if you accidentally gave back חולין טמאים chullin temein and
you didn't realize it was טמא, tamei, you didn't realize you weren't
supposed to give back טמא, tamei, תשלומין תשלומין. tashlumin tashlumin. It's good,
you paid back and we're done. במזיד bemazeid if you knew you
weren't supposed to and you did it anyway, אין תשלומין תשלומין. ein
tashlumin tashlumin. It doesn't count. And presumably you have to give back
חולין טהורין. chullin tehorin. So it's a case of fining the guy
who did it במזיד. bemazeid. Okay. You did something wrong במזיד, bemazeid,
you didn't fully pay him back something that would have been as
good for compensation or whatever, we're going to make you pay. We're
not going to let that count. Okay. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, the
חכמים Chachamim say, אחד זה ואחד זה תשלומין תשלומין echad zeh ve'echad
zeh tashlumin tashlumin וחוזר ומשלם חולין טהורין. vechozer umeshaleim chullin tehorin. Okay,
in either case it's good, meaning if it becomes תרומה. Terumah. And
the word תשלומין תשלומין tashlumin tashlumin means for the חכמים Chachamim is
the food became תרומה, Terumah, but we're going now make you pay
a second time. Okay. So what you gave him became תרומה Terumah
whether you're שוגג shogaig or מזיד, mazeid, but because you gave him
טמא tamei and not טהור, tahor, we're going actually now make you
pay a second time חולין טהורין. chullin tehorin. So the חכמים Chachamim
fine the guy whether שוגג shogaig or מזיד. mazeid. Yeah? You with
me? And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir only fines him in a case
of מזיד. mazeid. All right, that makes him pay a second time,
or that's how we're going to read רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir when
he said it didn't count, what he means is you have to
pay a second time. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואבינה
בה. v'avina bah. So before we get to applying this to our
case, we ask this. במזיד אמאי אין תשלומין תשלומין? bemazeid amai ein
tashlumin tashlumin? I don't get it, says the גמרא. Gemara. Even if
you willingly gave him back חולין טמאים, chullin temein, why does that
not count? What's so terrible? תבוא עליו ברכה, tavo alav beracha, which
is a little extreme statement, but okay. דאכל מיניה מידי דלא חזי
ליה. de'achal minei midi d'lo chazi lei. He ate תרומה טמאה, Terumah
temeiah, which at the time he ate it was essentially almost worthless,
okay? בימי טומאתו, bimei tumato, and he couldn't and the כהן Kohen
could not benefit from it when the כהן Kohen was טמא. tamei.
וקמשלם ליה מידי דחזי ליה בימי טומאתו. u'kameshaleim lei midi d'chazi lei
bimei tumato. And when he gave him back חולין, chullin, חולין טמא,
chullin tamei, the כהן Kohen could eat it when he was טמא.
tamei. Now of course the point is, fine, as he was paying
him back he was giving him חולין טמאים, chullin temein, but from
the moment it hit the כהן's Kohen hand it became תרומה טמאה
Terumah temeiah because in the act of giving it back it became
תרומה טמאה. Terumah temeiah. So it's a funny idea of תבוא עליו
ברכה, tavo alav beracha, but the גמרא Gemara is really just saying
is, why is it so bad that he gave him back חולין
טמא? chullin tamei? At the end of the day the כהן Kohen
got back what was taken from him. So why is it so
terrible? And it's even better in the sense that before it was
given back it was even better food, but anyway at the end
result it was at least equivalent to what was taken from him.
So why are we punishing this guy? So that we have to
figure that out before we can analyze the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda issue. So because of that logical question, the
גמרא Gemara rereads this ברייתא Baraita and here's what the גמרא Gemara
says. ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava, ואמרי לה כדי, ve'amri lah kedei, רבא
Rava said and some say anonymously it was said: חסורי מחסרא והכי
קתני. chasuri michasra vehachi katani. Yeah, this ברייתא Baraita is crazy that
we're fining the guy for giving back טמא tamei when all he
ate was טמא. tamei. So we're going to have to reread this
ברייתא Baraita so it makes more sense. והכי קתני, vehachi katani, here's
how you have to read. אכל תרומה טמאה משלם כל שהוא. achal
Terumah temeiah meshaleim kol shehu.
If you ate תרומה טמאה, Terumah temeiah,
then you can pay back anything, not meaning anything minimal value, but
meaning you can pay back טמא. tamei. You ate טמא, tamei, you
could pay back טמא tamei sure. So it's amazing, the גמרא Gemara
because of a logical question completely rereads the ברייתא, Baraita, right? I
mean we've seen that before. The ברייתא Baraita says if even though
it's טמא tamei you need to pay back טהור tahor and if
you do טמא tamei we're going to fine you. And the גמרא
Gemara says that doesn't make sense, you just ate טמא. tamei. Fine,
let's reread the ברייתא. Baraita. If you ate טמא, tamei, you can
pay back טמא. tamei. That's fine. So what's the case of the
ברייתא? Baraita? על אכל תרומה טהורה, al achal trumah tehorah, but the
case of the ברייתא Baraita we're going to say now is that
you ate טהור tahor תרומה. trumah. Now it's much more obvious why
you do something wrong if you pay back טמא. tamei. You ate
טהור tahor and you're paying back טמא. tamei. So in that case,
אכל תרומה טהורה משלם חולין טהורים. achal trumah tehorah meshalem chulin tehorim.
You have to pay back טהור tahor חולין chulin because now you're
giving the guy back something equivalent. שלם חולין טמאים, shilem chulin tmeim,
if you gave back חולין chulin טמא, tamei, so now he's getting
something worth a lot less. I should point out by the way
that תוספות Tosafot says רש"י Rashi says you only pay back the
same quantity. So if it's חולין טמאים, chulin tmeim, then you're giving
him back, so then he's really losing out significantly financially in the
deal, right? Because תרומה טמאה trumah tmeiah is worth like a hundredth
of תרומה טהורה trumah tehorah or something. Okay, where תוספות Tosafot says
no, no, no, the value has to be the same. So even
though you'll wind up giving him a hundred times as much, so
they say what's the difference, it's still the same value, but it's
sort of like the גמרא Gemara we said before by you know
the עידית קרקע idit karka and the זיבורית קרקע, ziborit karka, even
if it's the same value people would rather have you know the
the תרומה טהורה, trumah tehorah, less תרומה טהורה trumah tehorah than more
תרומה טמאה. trumah tmeiah. So one way or the other if you
ate תרומה טהורה, trumah tehorah, whether because of value or because of
convenience, because of cost or because of convenience, you have to pay
back חולין טהורים. chulin tehorim. What if you paid back חולין טמאים?
chulin tmeim? Okay, שלם חולין טמאים shilem chulin tmeim where obviously now
you're giving back something worse than what you ate. So in that
case, מהו? mahu? סומכוס אומר משום רבי מאיר, Sumchos omer mishum Rabi
Meir, בשוגג תשלומין תשלומין, beshogeg tashlumin tashlumin, if he was accidental it'll
be okay, דיעבד dieved it's okay. במזיד אין תשלומין תשלומין, bemezid ein
tashlumin tashlumin, in מזיד mezid it doesn't work, which we're going to
say means that the payment actually was חל, chal, it became תרומה
trumah what you gave him, that's idea that when you pay back
it becomes תרומה, trumah, that is take effect, but we're going to
make you pay a second time. So we're going to fine you
in the case of מזיד, mezid, not in the case of שוגג.
shogeg. וחכמים אומרים אחד זה ואחד זה תשלומין תשלומין, vachachamim omrim echad
zeh ve'echad zeh tashlumin tashlumin, whether שוגג shogeg or מזיד, mezid, the
payment became
תרומה, trumah, וחוזר ומשלם חולין טהורים, vechozer umeshalem chulin tehorim, but we're
going to fine you to pay the second time from חולין טהור.
chulin tahor. So basically what it boils down to is that you
are according to רבי מאיר Rabi Meir he's fining the case of
מזיד mezid and the חכמים Chachamim are fining even the case of
שוגג. shogeg. Okay, now how does that fit into our structure? So
let's take a look. דאמר רב אחא, de'amar Rav Acha, so all
that was just to start to get to now applying it to
our case, בריה דרב איקא, brei deRav Ika, הכא בקנס שוגג אטו
מזיד איכא בינייהו. hacha beknas shogeg atu mezid ika beinaihu.
So this is the debate: do we fine the guy who is
שוגג shogeg even
we're going to fine the guy who is מזיד mezid who who
knows he shouldn't be paying this back and he paid it back
anyway, him we're going to fine. Are we even going to fine
the guy who is שוגג? shogeg? דרבי מאיר סבר deRabi Meir savar
might as well read the brackets, לא קנסו שוגג אטו מזיד, lo
knasu shogeg atu mezid, וחכמים אומרים קנסו, vechachamim omrim knasu, right? So
the חכמים Chachamim say you have to pay back even if you're
שוגג shogeg a second time. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what's
the question? So the question is:
why did רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda according to... wait, according to רבי
מאיר, Rabi Meir, okay, why
we did not fine? But what the guy did wrong was not
really like a תורה Torah I mean when he ate תרומה trumah
he shouldn't have eaten תרומה, trumah, that was a תורה Torah violation.
But paying back one type of תרומה trumah as opposed to another,
one type of חולין chulin as opposed to another type of חולין,
chulin, isn't like a תורה Torah violation, okay? And we know that
normally when you're not doing a תורה Torah violation in your act,
רבי מאיר, Rabi Meir, right? When it's only דרבנן, derabbanan, רבי מאיר
Rabi Meir does fine you if it's not a תורה Torah violation.
So here, why didn't רבי מאיר Rabi Meir fine the guy who
was paying back the תרומה טמאה trumah tmeiah on the חולין טמאים?
chulin tmeim? So the גמרא Gemara says: הכי השתא? hachi hashta? Wait,
what type of question is that? התם גברא לשלומי קא מכוין. hatam
gavra leshlumei ka michavein. You're actually there trying to make good. You're
paying back. So so we're not going to fine a guy, if
somebody damages somebody's property בשוגג, beshogeg, that's like a bad act that
you did. You did it בשוגג beshogeg and it's only דרבנן derabbanan
or whatever and you're not going to be careful enough we're going
to fine. So he fines the guy who does a דרבנן derabbanan
בשוגג beshogeg when the דרבנן derabbanan was a bad act, something bad
that the person he he damaged property, so we have to stop
that behavior. So we're going to fine the guy. It's only דרבנן
derabbanan and people are going to be too lax. But this case,
the guy's trying to make good. So okay, he did it in
the wrong way. He paid back טמא tamei rather than טהור. tahor.
We're not going to start fining people when they're actually trying to
make good. Okay, התם גברא לשלומי קא מכוין, hatam gavra leshlumei ka
michavein, he's trying to pay back. אנוסי ובלי קניסה, anusei uveli knisa,
we're going to fine him? Yes, Charlie.
Well, I pay back exactly what I stole.
No, no, no, the גמרא Gemara remember reread the ברייתא Baraita so
that you ate חולין chulin תרומה טהורה trumah tehorah and you pay
back חולין טמאים. chulin tmeim. Right, but even so, says the גמרא,
Gemara, you're still trying to make good, so you did it wrong
and you were a little sloppy about it, but we're not going
to fine you in that case. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, let's
hear another case. המעשר בשבת, hame'aser beShabbat, בשוגג יאכל במזיד לא יאכל.
beshogeg yochel bemezid lo yochel. So you violated... Shabbos was a rabbinic
violation. You took תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros on שבת. Shabbos. That's a
rabbinic violation of שבת. Shabbos. So the הלכה halakha is בשוגג be-shogeg
you can benefit from it and מזיד meizid you can't. And we're
assuming that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So here's the problem: that again,
that's a rabbinic violation, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir should fine the
guy if he did a rabbinic violation, right? He took מעשר maaser
on שבת. Shabbos. Why is he not fining the guy? So the
גמרא Gemara says: הכי השתא? hachi hashta? Wait, what type of comparison
is that? התם גברא לתקוני קמכוון, hasam gavra letikuni kamikhaven, אנן ניקום
ונקנסיה? anan neiqu veniqnesei?
It's true he violated שבת Shabbos rabbinically, but the act was fundamentally
trying to do something good. He was like doing a מצוה. mitzvah.
He was separating תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'maasros. So it would be like
very, you know, counter policy interests to fine a guy who like
is trying to do the right thing. Okay. All right. תא שמע.
ta shma. Come in here. המטביל כלים בשבת. hamatbil kelim bishabbos.
Similar case where you violated שבת Shabbos but you're in the middle
of doing the מצוה. mitzvah. המטביל כלים בשבת. hamatbil kelim bishabbos.
You're immersing your vessels in a מקוה, mikvah, which you're not allowed
to do on שבת Shabbos and that's rabbinic. Okay? בשוגג ישתמש בהן,
beshogeg yeshtamesh bahem, במזיד לא ישתמש בהן. bemeizid lo yeshtamesh bahem. If
it's accidentally, though, you can use them because we don't fine you.
If it's intentionally, we don't allow you to use them. You're not
allowed to use a כלי, kli, a vessel, that has not been
dunked into the מקוה. mikvah. So the גמרא Gemara says: why didn't
we fine you in a case of שוגג? shogeg? It was a
rabbinic violation according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. We're supposed to fine
people who do rabbinic violations. So the גמרא Gemara says no: הכי
השתא? hachi hashta? How can you make the comparison? התם גברא לטהורי
קמכוון, hasam gavra letahorei kamikhaven, אנן ניקום ונקנסיה? anan neiqu veniqnesei? He's
trying to purify his vessels.
We're going to go ahead and fine him? Okay. So basically, even
though רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir fines people בשוגג beshogeg by דרבנן, de-rabbanan,
that's when fundamentally the act is a bad act. If the act
is fundamentally a מצוה mitzvah act, even if it involves a violation
of a דרבנן de-rabbanan violation, if he's fundamentally trying to pay back
and make good, we're not going to
apply fines. Okay, ורמי דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה בדרבנן. urami de-Rabbi Yehuda
a-de-Rabbi Yehuda be-de-rabbanan. So now we're going to shift our focus to
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Yes.
Did you cover the case of the דם שנטמא וזרקו? dam she-nitma
ve-zarko?
Oh, I didn't. You're right. Let's go back. Oh, thank you for
catching me. Okay, we're going to double back. Thank you. תא שמע.
ta shma. So it's actually two lines after the parentheses, about ten
lines from the bottom. Thank you for catching that. תא שמע: ta
shma: דם שנטמא וזרקו. dam she-nitma ve-zarko. So דם dam became טמא,
tamei, and of a קרבן, korban, and it was thrown on the
מזבח. mizbeach. It was put on the מזבח. mizbeach. Now, the הלכה
halakha is that even if that was done במזיד, bemeizid, the קרבן
korban is still good because there's a principle that the ציץ tzitz
is מרצה. meratzeh. The ציץ tzitz that the כהן גדול kohen gadol
wears on his forehead allows that even blood that is טמא tamei
that was put on the מזבח mizbeach still is מכפר, mechaper, even
במזיד. bemeizid. At least, so that's the הלכה halakha is that it
will work even במזיד. bemeizid. But now we're going to deal with
the דרבנן. de-rabbanan. בשוגג הורצה. beshogeg hurtzah. If it was done accidentally,
then we'll say the קרבן korban was good. במזיד, bemeizid, if it
was done willfully, you know, a willful violation, לא הורצה. lo hurtzah.
It doesn't count. Now, of course, the point is one minute: who
are we fining? The כהן kohen is the one doing the עבירה,
averah, putting the blood on the מזבח, mizbeach, and we're saying that
the בעלים's ba'alim קרבן korban wasn't good? So רש״י Rashi says no,
no, no. The בעלים, ba'alim, the owners, were יצא yotzei the חיוב
chiyuv קרבן. korban. When we're saying the blood didn't work in this
case if it was willful, it means you don't get to eat
the meat. And most קרבנות, korbanos, the meat is eaten by the
כהנים, kohanim, right? שלמים shelamim it's eaten by the owners, but most
קרבנות korbanos it's eaten by the כהנים. kohanim. So the כהנים kohanim
threw the blood, they knew they weren't supposed to, it was מזיד,
meizid, it was טמא, tamei, and therefore we say you don't get
to eat the meat. Okay, okay fine. But now the point is:
why don't we say that throwing the blood is actually an amazing
idea? Throwing the blood when it's טמא, tamei, since the ציץ tzitz
allows for it to work, רש״י Rashi says there would not be
a תורה Torah violation to throw, to put the blood on the
altar when it's טמא. tamei. Since the ציץ tzitz says, the presence
of the ציץ tzitz says that this blood can be מכפר mechaper
even though it's טמא, tamei, you're actually allowed from a תורה Torah
perspective לכתחילה le-chatchilah to do it. So doing this is a rabbinic
violation. So if it's a rabbinic violation, why did רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir not fine even in a case of שוגג? shogeg? Right? Because
again, we're assuming רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir fines שוגג shogeg in a
case of rabbinic violation. So if this דם dam is טמא tamei
blood, it's a rabbinic violation to put it on the מזבח, mizbeach,
why do we let you get away with it בשוגג? beshogeg? So
the גמרא Gemara says: same thing. Well, same thing that we've been
seeing. אמר לך רבי מאיר: amar le-kha Rabbi Meir: הכי השתא? hachi
hashta? What type of comparison is that? התם גברא לכפורי קמכוון, hasam
gavra le-chapporei kamikhaven, there you're trying to atone and do a מצוה
mitzvah and so on, so אנן ניקום ונקנסיה? anan neiqu veniqnesei? Okay,
so you made a mistake and you were sloppy and you didn't
realize that the דם dam was טמא. tamei. We're not going to
start fining people when they're involved in, you know, this type of...
כהנים kohanim now have to worry that simple mistakes that they make
when they're doing the עבודה, avodah, you know, is going to fine
them? Like that's not good policy
to be applying fines to people that are trying to do מצוות
mitzvos and the עבודה avodah and so on. Okay, and then similarly
the גמרא Gemara said the similar answer by the case about taking
מעשר maaser on שבת Shabbos and המטביל כלים matbil kelim on שבת.
Shabbos. Yes, those were שוגג shogeg violations of דרבנן, de-rabbanan, and we
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir the logic normally is we do
fine, but not in the time when somebody's doing a מצוה. mitzvah.
Okay, thank you for catching that. ורמי דרבי יהודה urami de-Rabbi Yehuda
last line of נ״ד, nun-dalet, see I'm
so... We're doing a pretty good job. ורמי דרבי יהודה דרבי יהודה
בדרבנן. U-rami d'Rabbi Yehuda d'Rabbi Yehuda bid'rabbanan. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
we said בדרבנן bid'rabbanan says we don't make a fine in a
case of שוגג. shogeg. I'm going to show you some cases where
it seems like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does make a fine בדרבנן
bid'rabbanan in a case of שוגג. shogeg. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught a
ברייתא. braisa. נפלו
נתפצעו, Nafelu nitpatzu, top of נ"ד עמוד ב', nun-daled amud-bet, get to
turn the page. נפלו נתפצעו אחד בשוגג ואחד במזיד לא יעלו דברי
רבי מאיר. Nafelu nitpatzu echad b'shogeg v'echad b'meizid lo ya'alu d'vrei Rebbe
Meir. You have certain nuts which are considered to be a דבר
חשוב. davar chashuv. They're considered to be like important, you know, and
therefore because each one is like a precious thing, it's not בטל
batel if it gets mixed up. So you have a nut that's
ערלה, orla, let's say, and can't be eaten, and it gets mixed
up with a hundred similar nuts, but because we're dealing with a
particular type of nut, okay, the גמרא Gemara talks about particular type
of almonds or whatever that are very valuable or that are, you
know, have a lot of significance. So even if it's mixed up
with a thousand, it's not בטל. batel. Normally you say something is
בטל ברוב batel b'rov or בשישים. b'shishim. Here it's not בטל batel
even in a thousand because it's considered a דבר חשוב. davar chashuv.
Now what happens if it gets cracked? And it gets mixed up
and it's all cracked? Well then it loses its חשיבות, chashivus, it
loses its importance, okay, and in that case it does become בטל.
batel. So here you have, you've got your nuts that are all
mixed up and one of them is ערלה orla and it's all,
you can't eat any of it. Then whoops, accidentally they all get
crushed and now it's all okay. Okay, so you might, that's a
problem caused by אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה. ein mevatlin issur l'chatchilah. You're
not allowed to intentionally do something that creates ביטול. bittul. Okay, what's
say if happened? So the first opinion is whether it is שוגג
shogeg or מזיד, meizid, you know, you are, it's not going to
be בטל. batel. So that's רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir. So רבי מאיר,
Rebbe Meir, let's remember what רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says. This is
a דרבנן derabbanan problem, right? It's a דרבנן derabbanan problem. You can't
be מבטל איסור לכתחילה. mevatel issur l'chatchilah. By the way, the only
reason it's also a reason it's a דרבנן derabbanan problem is because
only rabbinically do we say that this isn't בטל. batel. דאורייתא De-oraisa
this is בטל. batel. Okay, so this whole thing is a rabbinic
problem, and you violated it בשוגג. be-shogeg. So רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
is going to say we're going to fine you. So רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir is consistent. Okay, it's a fining you in a case
of a דרבנן derabbanan violation. But here's the problem. דברי רבי מאיר
ורבי יהודה. Divrei Rebbe Meir v'Rebbe Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda joined
רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir's team here. So what is רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda doing joining רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir's team? This is a דרבנן
derabbanan and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda should say
we do not fine you by a דרבנן. derabbanan. So we're going
to have to see. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים בשוגג יעלו במזיד
לא יעלו. Rebbe Yose v'Rebbe Shimon omrim b'shogeg ya'alu b'meizid lo ya'alu.
They say no. By בשוגג be-shogeg we don't fine, we only fine
by במזיד. be-meizid. Okay, so now the question is what's רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda doing switching sides? והכא היי דאורייתא חד בתרי בטיל. V'hacha
hai d'oraisa chad b'trei batel. Biblically speaking, one is something is בטל
batel in two, like two against one even if it's like not,
if it doesn't give off taste, if it's like solids and solids.
ורבנן הוא דגזרו, V'rabbanan hu d'gazar, and the rabbis just say that
something that's חשוב chashuv isn't בטל. batel. וקא קניס רבי יהודה, V'ka-knis
Rebbe Yehuda, and here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you violated this דרבנן,
derabbanan, and the whole problem was rabbinic to begin with and being
מבטל איסור mevatel issur is a דרבנן derabbanan problem, although the גמרא
Gemara doesn't say that. So the whole thing is rabbinic. So why
is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda making the fine? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
usually doesn't fine by דרבנן. derabbanan. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
התם היינו טעמא דרבי יהודה משום דאתי לארומי. Hasam hainu ta'ama d'Rebbe
Yehuda mishum d'ati l'arumay. This is the reason רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
because you're going to scheme. You're going to say it was an
accident, like sort of I said, like whoops. Accidentally, now of course
you could say that's true in all these cases. How can you
ever make a distinction between מזיד meizid and שוגג shogeg if you
allow the שוגג shogeg guy off? He's going to claim he'll do
it במזיד be-meizid and he's going to claim he was a שוגג.
shogeg. But the difference is that all those other cases there's very
little incentive to be doing it. Like okay, if you're a רשע
rasha you want to hurt somebody's property, you're going to do it
במזיד be-meizid and say you were שוגג, shogeg, okay. But there's very
little incentive to be doing those types of things. Here, all of
your nuts are going to go to waste. All you have to
do is accidentally get them crushed and you'll be okay. So there's
a very strong temptation in this case. So because this case is
a strong temptation to do it במזיד be-meizid and to claim it's
an accident, we want to close off that avenue. So here's a
case that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree. All right, so now
one more case. ורמי דרבי
יוסי אדרבי יוסי. V'rami d'Rebbe Yose a'dRebbe Yose. Now we've introduced another
person, רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yose, right? רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon said we do it בשוגג be-shogeg it's okay. So
here it's a דרבנן, derabbanan, here's a possible, you know, sort of
like whoops type of ארומי, arumay, and nevertheless רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose
says we're not going to fine in the case of שוגג. shogeg.
Okay, so now let's compare that to another case of רבי יוסי.
Rebbe Yose. דתנן נטיעה של ערלה ושל כלאי הכרם שנתערבו בנטיעות אחרות.
Detnan netia shel orla v'shel kilai ha-kerem she-nit'arbu b'netiot acherot. You have
one planting, one shoot of ערלה orla or of כלאי הכרם kilai
ha-kerem that got mixed up with all your other plantings. Okay, and
the problem now is that it's not בטל batel and you can't
benefit from anything. Now once you pick the fruit from the tree,
the one of the reasons it's not בטל batel is also because
it's מחובר לקרקע, mechubar l'karka, that gives it significance and it can't
lose its identity. But once you pick the fruit off of the
vine and the fruit gets mixed up... fruit will be בטל. battel.
Okay, so picking the fruit is sort of like crushing the nut.
It's allowing the ביטול bittel to take effect. Okay, אם הרי זה
לא ילקט, im harei zeh lo yilakeit, you're not allowed to pick
the fruit, ואם ליקט יעלו באחד ומאתים, ve'im likat ya'alu be'echad umatayim,
and if you did, then it's בטל battel 1 and 200 because
that's the הלכה halacha of ערלה orlah is 1 and 200. ובדלא
שיתכוין ללקוט, ubid'lo sheyitkavein lilkot,
as long as you don't pick with the intention, not you don't
pick without intending to pick, but you don't pick with the intention
of making it בטל. battel. רבי יוסי אומר אפילו מתכוין ללקוט, Rebbi
Yossi omer afilu mitkavein lilkot,
even if you were מזיד, meizid, יעלו באחד ומאתים, ya'alu be'echad umatayim,
it could be בטל. battel. So here's crazy, I mean not crazy,
but Rebbi Yossi is very lenient. In the case of the whoops
by the nuts, okay, he said, I'm not going to fine you
in a case of שוגג, shogeg, but I will in a case
of מזיד. meizid. Here, in the case of the shoot of the
ערלה orlah that gets mixed up, he even says even in a
case of מזיד, meizid, I'm not going to fine you and the
thing will be בטל. battel. So what's going on there? So, so
the גמרא Gemara says, הא איתמר עלה אמר רבה חזקה אין אדם
אוסר כרמו בנטייה אחת. ha itmar alah amar Rabbah chazakah ein adam
oser karmo binetiyah achat. No, a person normally will not make his
vineyard forbidden with one planting. וכן כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן
חזקה אין אדם אוסר כרמו בנטייה אחת. vechen ki ata Ravin amar
Rabbi Yochanan chazakah ein adam oser karmo binetiyah achat. Now what does
that mean? Of course you're not intentionally going to plant it. So
what does that mean? So if you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י
Rashi says,
where's רש״י? Rashi? אין אדם אוסר כרמו בנטייה אחת, ein adam oser
karmo binetiyah achat, like
right a little under the משנה. mishnah. He says, אין לך אדם
נוטע ערלה בין שאר נטיעות בלא סימן ואוסר כרמו בשביל נטיעה אחת.
ein lecha adam noteia orlah bein shear netiyot belo siman ve'oser karmo
bishvil netiyah achat. Nobody normally would ever have done that planting without
have trying to take a precaution, right? Why would you be so
stupid to have planted the ערלה orlah thing without having taken some
precaution? וכיון דלא שכיחא לא אחמור רבנן. vekeivan d'lo shechicha lo achmur
rabanan. Okay,
so basically it means like this whole scenario that you accidentally got
an ערלה orlah tree planted among your other trees or a, you
know, an ערלה orlah vine planted among your other vines is like
never should happen. You know, nobody would be stupid enough to do
that. People would take precautions. So if it happened once in a
blue moon, we're not going to fine the outcomes of that. Okay,
whereas things getting mixed up, nuts getting mixed up, that's a more
common scenario and therefore at least we have to fine in a
case of שוגג, shogeg, okay? So a whole range of different concerns
about when do we fine by שוגג, shogeg, when do we not
fine by שוגג, shogeg, and one scenario at the very end where
even in a case of מזיד meizid we don't fine, but fundamentally
the battleground is when do we fine by שוגג shogeg and when
not, and sometimes the positions are like diametrically opposed. Great, we got
that done. Let's start the next case.
הכהנים שפגלו במקדש מזידין חייבים. hacohanim shepiglu bamikdash mezidin chayavim. Okay, so
this is we quoted this earlier and some actually have the גרסא
girsa in the משנה mishnah שוגגין פטורים. shogegin peturim. But anyway, it's
implied. So כהן kohen does פיגול, pigul, he שחטס shechts a קרבן
korban or he throws the blood and he has in his mind
to eat it at the wrong time. Okay, in that case the
הלכה halacha is if he does it willfully then he is חייב,
chayav, he has to pay the owners because he ruined the owners'
קרבן. korban. And if he does it accidentally he doesn't, so it's
another example of היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikkar, right? And there
we
and he's going to have to pay. Now the גמרא Gemara switches
because we've already analyzed היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikkar, so it's
going to switch from the question of damages to the question of
do we trust somebody when they say something happened? There's no evidence
that it happened. I'm coming and I'm telling you guess what, I
put a שרץ sheretz on your תרומה, trumah, okay, or the I'm
a כהן kohen and I went and I שחטד shechted your thing
with a thought of פיגול. pigul. So there's one question do I
have to pay, but there's another question why should you believe me?
Okay, maybe you're lying. All right, so let's take a look. תנו
רבנן היה עושה עמו בטהרות. tanu rabanan hayah oseh imo betaharot. You
were you were working with somebody, you know, and you were טהור
tahor and you wanted and you had to keep everything טהור, tahor,
maybe it was תרומה trumah or maybe the person wanted to use
חולין chullin that was טהור, tahor, but they were very careful to
be keeping everything טהור. tahor. ואמר לו, ve'amar lo, and then you
said to the guy you were working with, you were like he
was hiring you to help him out in his field or whatever
he was doing, you know, preparing washing his fruit, who knows what,
and you said to him, טהרות
שעשיתי עמך נטמאו. taharot she'asiti imcha nitme'u. You know what, I want
to tell you that the stuff we were working on, it became
טמא. tamei. היה עושה עמו בזבחים. hayah oseh imo bizvachim. Okay, or
you were a כהן kohen and you were doing a קרבן korban
for somebody. ואמר לו זבחים שעשיתי עמך נתפגלו. ve'amar lo zvachim she'asiti
imcha nitpiglu. The קרבן korban that I was bringing for you became
פיגול. pigul. נאמן. ne'eman. You're believed, there's not a question of תשלומין,
tashlumim, you're believed to say that that happened and now the thing
is אסור. assur. Okay,
אבל אומר לו, aval omer lo, but if you say to him,
טהרות שעשיתי עמך ביום פלוני נטמאו. taharot she'asiti imcha beyom ploni nitme'u.
You know, remember three days ago when we were doing that stuff
and working on your apples, I forgot to tell you, the stuff
it became טמא. tamei. Or זבחים שעשיתי עמך ביום פלוני נתפגלו. zvachim
she'asiti imcha beyom ploni nitpiglu. Oh, that קרבן korban I brought for
you three days ago it became פיגול. pigul. So I tell it
to you about something that happened in the past, in that case
אינו נאמן, eino ne'eman, you're not believed. So the גמרא Gemara asks
the obvious question, מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? mai shena reisha
u'mai shena seifa? What difference does it make? Either you're believed or
not. So two very different interpretations. אמר אביי כל שבידו נאמן. amar
Abaye kol shebeyado ne'eman. Abaye says the reason you're believed when you're
saying it happened now is because right now... Now you're in the
middle of working on the טהרות tahros or you're in the middle
of bringing the קרבן. korban. רש״י Rashi says the scenario is the
כהן kohen שחט shachted the קרבן, korban, but he didn't yet throw
the blood. So the basic point is it's sort of like a
מיגו, migo, like if I were lying then I could just do
it right now if I wanted to do it. I could make
this stuff טמא tamei right now, I could make this stuff פיגול
pigul right now. So since I have the ability to do it,
that gives me a special believability, to you know, a special sense
of like I'm in a way almost the owner of this, you
know, because I could control its fate, so therefore I'm believed about
it. Okay, that's what אביי Abaye says. According to אביי, Abaye, it
would only be true if you were ממש mamash still in the
middle of dealing with it. All right. ורבא אמר, v'Rava amar, and
רבא Rava says it doesn't have to be בידו. beyado. Here's the
reason, you waited too long. Okay, in the second case. כיון דאשכחיה
ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי keivan d'ashkechei v'lo amar lei v'lo midi
because since like why if you say to me, oh by the
way, the קרבן korban I did for you three days ago became
פיגול, pigul, what would my first reaction to you be?
Why didn't you tell me then?
Oh by the way, you know, and by the way I ate
the קרבן korban too. Right.
By the way, the stuff we were working on, you know on
Tuesday, it didn't it became טמא. tamei. Why didn't you tell me?
We were working all together Tuesday, why'd you wait till now? So
the fact that you waited, right, makes the claim suspicious. But it
doesn't have to be ממש בידו. mamash beyado. So if I came
back after doing the קרבן korban and it's all fully brought and
I informed you, or I was working in the field and I
came back at the end of the day and I reported it
to you, I would be believed even though it's no longer בידו.
beyado. The problem is that I waited too long and it under
and it creates suspicion about the veracity of what I'm saying. כיון
דאשכחיה keivan d'ashkechei you found him ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי v'lo
amar lei v'lo midi and you didn't say anything, ולבתר הכי אשכחיה
u'le'vasar hachi ashkechei and then on a later day you bumped into
him דאמר ליה d'amar lei and you said to him, and therefore
you're not believed. Let's read one case. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה hahu
d'amar lei l'chaverei a person said to his friend, טהרות שעשיתי עמך
ביום פלוני נטמאו. tahros she'asisi imcha b'yom ploni nitme'u. You know, that
those טהרות tahros we were working on on Tuesday they became טמא.
tamei. אתא לקמיה דרבי אמי ata lekamei d'Rabbi Ami he came before
רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. אמר ליה amar lei שורת הדין shuras hadin
the הלכה halacha is, אינו נאמן, eino ne'eman, he's not believed because
he said it happened a few days ago. אמר לפניו רבי אסי,
amar lefanav Rabbi Assi, רבי אסי Rabbi Assi said to רבי אמי,
Rabbi Ami, רבי אתה אומר כן? Rebbi ata omer kein? So is
it simply
really Rebbi you say this or the way רש״י Rashi reads it
is Rebbi that's your position, but הכי אמר רבי יוחנן hachi amar
Rabbi Yochanan משום רבי יוסי, mishum Rabbi Yossi, here's what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says in the name of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. מה
אעשה שהתורה האמינתו? ma e'eseh she'ha'Torah he'eminaso?
No, even if he says it happened on Tuesday you're believed, the
תורה Torah believed him. So why did where do we see that
the תורה Torah believed him? Okay, the גמרא Gemara says היכן התורה
האמינתו? heichan ha'Torah he'eminaso? אמר רבי יצחק בר ביסנא Amar Rabbi Yitzchak
bar Bisna כהן גדול ביום הכפורים יוכיח. Kohen Gadol b'Yom haKippurim yochiach.
Here's where the כהן kohen is believed, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur דכי אמר d'chi amar right
he's in the בית המקדש Beis haMikdash all by himself, let's say
he would have come out and said that something bad happened with
the קרבן. korban. Presumably we'd believe him, I don't know how, maybe
we wouldn't believe him, but he's presuming we would believe. Okay, דכי
אמר פיגול מהימן, d'chi amar pigul meheiman, okay,
if he were to come out and say it was פיגול pigul
we'd believe him. So that would have happened after the fact, nobody
else would have been around and we would believe him. So the
גמרא Gemara says, now ומנא ידעינן u'mena yadinan where do we know
that? וכתיב ve'chtiv כל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד kol adam lo
yihiyeh b'Ohel Moed
because nobody else can be there, אלא לאו משום דמהימן ela lav
mishum d'meheiman it must be that he's believed, so you see even
after the fact he's believed. So the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא דשמענא
דפגיל u'dilma d'sham'ana d'paggil
maybe we heard him, maybe we were outside of the היכל, Heichal,
we were in the עזרה Azarah and we hear the כהן kohen
say, I can't wait to eat this stuff on you know to
be זורק zorek this whatever for you know two days from now.
So that case the גמרא Gemara says אי לאו דמהימן ei lav
d'meheiman אע"ג דשמעינן נמי לא מהימן. af al gav d'sham'inan nami lo
meheiman. No,
if he weren't believed then even if we heard his voice coming
out from in there we wouldn't believe him. Why not? דדילמא בתר
הכי קאמר d'dilma batar hachi ka'amar
because maybe let's say he was saying, wow, I'm שוחט shachting this
animal I'm שוחט shachting I'm you know I'm carrying the blood with
the intention of throwing the blood tomorrow. So when did he say
that? Who knows that he said that when he was carrying the
blood? Maybe he was saying that after he threw the blood and
he was just trying to deceive all of us. So obviously we
don't really have direct knowledge about what happened, and therefore it must
be that he's believed. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, there's
still another explanation, ודילמא דחזייה בפשפש u'dilma d'chazeih b'pishpesh
maybe we saw him through one of those little you know like
peepholes that they had peepholes into the עזרה Azarah and into the
היכל Heichal and into the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, I mean into
the היכל Heichal into the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So how do
you know even though nobody was with him, maybe we still could
have been spying on him, we had our video cameras up there?
So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. Okay fine, it's not an
absolute proof. So that was an interesting proof from the תורה, Torah,
but the one thing I do want to say is the case
of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not the case where he
had a chance to tell us later on, right maybe he told
us immediately when he exited. So this case on the guy said
oh three days ago it became a problem, right that could be
that that's consistent with רבא, Rava, could be it was a case
where this was
the
first. It's only a problem when you should have said it earlier
and the fact that you didn't makes your current claim a suspicious
one.
Okay, checked it in another animal in that case because it's so
common. What? They had made another
check?
Yeah, they would have to bring another sacrifice. Okay, so we'll end
here and we... keep going? You want to? I think we keep
going. All
right fine, fine let's go, let's go. We'll try to get to
the משנה. Mishnah. All right, excellent. Okay. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבי אמי.
Hahu de-ata lekamei de-Rabbi Ami. Somebody came to Rabbi Ami. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, ספר תורה שכתבתי לפלוני אזכרות שלא לכתבתי לשמה. Sefer Torah
she-katavti liploni azkarot she-lo lo katavti lishmah. A
ספר תורה Sefer Torah I wrote for a certain person, I have
to be honest with you, I didn't write the שם השם, Shem
Hashem, I didn't have the כוונה. kavanah. Okay, so now this is
no longer בידו. be-yado. Now Rabbi Ami, if you'll remember, said in
the case when the guy said, "Oh, it happened on Tuesday," whatever,
remember that? He said Rabbi Ami said, you know, שעתו הדין אינו
נאמן, she'ato ha-din eino ne'eman, you're not believed. Okay, and that seemed
to be
even regardless of whether you did or did not have an opportunity
to tell him earlier. It seems that Rabbi Ami was of the
position that anything that's not right now בידו, be-yado, like אביי, Abaye,
anything that's in the past you're not believed about. Okay, so here's
what he's going to say. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ספר תורה ביד
מי? Sefer Torah be-yad mi?
Who's holding onto the ספר תורה? Sefer Torah? That's the question of
בידו, be-yado, who has control over it, right? אמר ליה ביד לוקח.
Amar lei be-yad loke'ach. I already gave it back to the purchaser.
So אמר ליה, Amar lei, נאמן אתה להפסיד שכרך ואי אתה נאמן
להפסיד ספר תורה. ne'eman atah lehafsid sekharekha ve-i atah ne'eman lehafsid Sefer
Torah. So if you're admitting that you made it פסול, pasul, you're
basically saying you didn't do your job. So now you're believed to
say that you won't get paid,
but you're not believed to פסול pasul the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah.
And that's a little bit bizarre because you could say one minute,
since the guy is not going to believe me about the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah and he's going to use it and it's going
to have the status of a כשר ספר תורה, kasher Sefer Torah,
right? So if it's going to have a status of a כשר
ספר תורה, kasher Sefer Torah, why can't I get paid for it?
I gave him a כשר ספר תורה. kasher Sefer Torah. So it's
a little funny. Anyway, fine, but that's that was his פסק. psak.
Okay, but what we see is the issue was בידו. be-yado. It
wasn't in his once it wasn't in his control, he wasn't believed.
But to hurt himself financially, you know, that you are believed to
make claims against your own financial interests. Okay. אמר ליה רבי
ירמיה, Amar lei Rabbi Yirmiyah, Rabbi Yirmiyah said to him, נהי דהפסיד
שכר אזכרות שכר ספר תורה כולה מי הפסיד? nehi de-hifsid sekhar azkarot,
sekhar Sefer Torah kuleiah mi hifsid?
Fine, he shouldn't get paid for writing שם השם Shem Hashem because
he did that incorrectly according to his own testimony, but why shouldn't
he get paid for writing the rest of the ספר תורה? Sefer
Torah? So he just loses the amount of time it took to
write the שם השם. Shem Hashem. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said back to him,
אין, in, yes, שכל ספר תורה שאין אזכרותיה כתובות לשמה אינה שווה
כלום. she-kol Sefer Torah she-ein azkaroteha ketuvot lishmah einah shaveh klum. Yeah,
because if you don't have שם השם Shem Hashem written correctly, you
can't rewrite שם השם. Shem Hashem. What are you going to do,
erase שם השם? Shem Hashem? Right? So there's no way to fix
it. So since there's no way to fix it, it's not worth
anything. All right. So
the גמרא Gemara says, וליעבר עליה קולמוס ולקדשיה? ve-li'aber aleiah kulmus u-lekadesheiah?
One minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, you can't erase שם השם, Shem
Hashem, but why not just re-ink שם השם? Shem Hashem? Won't that
work?
כמאן? Keman? Now that's suggestion who's that going like? נימא דלא כרבי
יהודה? Naima de-lo ke-Rabbi Yehudah? No, I mean, or why if you
couldn't do it, why couldn't you do it? נימא דלא כרבי יהודה.
Naima de-lo ke-Rabbi Yehudah. Let's say it's not like Rabbi Yehuda. It's
תנן. tnan. הרי שהיה צריך לכתוב את השם, Harei she-hayah tzarikh likhtov
et ha-shem, you'd have to write שם השם Shem Hashem in a
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, let's say, ונתכוון לכתוב יהודה, ve-nitkaven likhtov Yehudah,
and you had in mind to write יהודה. Yehudah. Okay, so you
had the wrong thing in mind but then accidentally you write the
right thing. וטעה ולא הטיל בו דלת. Ve-ta'ah ve-lo hetil bo dalet.
You didn't have the דלת dalet and you wound up writing שם
השם. Shem Hashem. So basically you wrote שם השם Shem Hashem without
intending to write שם השם. Shem Hashem. Okay, how do you fix
it? מעביר עליו קולמוס ומקדשו דברי רבי יהודה. Ma'avir alav kulmus u-mekadesho,
divrei Rabbi Yehudah. Rabbi Yehuda says you could just re-ink it. וחכמים
אומרים אין השם מן המובחר. ve-Chakhamim omrim ein ha-shem min ha-muvchar. No,
you can't because that's not respectful for שם השם. Shem Hashem. Okay,
so what you see is so why did you feel the whole
ספר תורה Sefer Torah was פסול? pasul? According to Rabbi Yehuda there's
a way to fix it. Just re-ink it. Are you is your
position against Rabbi Yehuda? So the גמרא Gemara says, אפילו תימא רבי
יהודה. Afilu teima Rabbi Yehudah. In this case even Rabbi Yehuda would
agree there's no way to fix it. Why not? עד כאן לא
קאמר רבי יהודה אלא בחדא אזכרה. Ad kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Yehudah
ela be-chada azkarah. He only said by one שם השם. Shem Hashem.
אבל דכולי ספר תורה לא, aval de-kulei Sefer Torah lo, to have
to re-ink all the שם השם Shem Hashem in the ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, no, it's not good. משום דמיחזי כמנומר. mishum de-mikhzei ke-menumar.
It looks spotted. Meaning the fact that every שם השם Shem Hashem
is a re-ink, the ספר תורה Sefer Torah does not look like
it's a consistent type of a כתב. ksav. And therefore that's not
appropriate and therefore whether that's a דאורייתא de-Oraita פסול psul of a
ספר תורה Sefer Torah or דרבנן de-Rabbanan פסול, psul, but either way
according to your claim you gave him a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
that was effectively worthless. Ironically, although now he's going to go ahead
and use it. But according to your claim you don't deserve to
get paid. So can he use it? He can use it according
to this it's very bizarre. He can use it but you don't
get paid. Okay. ההוא דאתא לקמיה
דרבי אבהו.
Hahu de-ata lekamei
de-Rabbi Abbahu. Somebody came to Rabbi Abbahu. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ספר
תורה שכתבתי לפלוני גוילים שלו לא עיבדתי לשמה. Sefer Torah she-katavti liploni
gevilin shelo lo ibadeti lishmah.
The גוילים gevilin I did not sort of process lishmah. He and
the קלפים klaphim with the right כוונה kavana ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
and therefore they can't be used, and the whole ספר תורה Sefer
Torah is
פסול. pasul. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ספר תורה ביד מי? Sefer Torah
b'yad mi? Who's holding onto the ספר תורה Sefer Torah right now?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, ביד לוקח, B'yad lokeiach, the purchaser. אמר ליה,
Amar lo, מתוך שאתה נאמן להפסיד שכרך אתה נאמן להפסיד ספר תורה.
Mitoch she'ata ne'eman l'hafsid secharacha ata ne'eman l'hafsid Sefer Torah.
Since your claim will mean that you'll lose your fee, so if
you're willing to so much come forth and be honest, it's like
a מיגו, migo, makes a lot of sense, just as circumstantial evidence,
right? It might not be בידו, b'yado, but give me a break.
Why would this guy lie about it? He's going to lose his
whole fee. So if you're going to tell this and we know
that the consequence is you'll lose your fee, obviously you're telling the
truth and you'll be believed to פסל posul the ספר תורה. Sefer
Torah. Okay.
So this contradicts Rabbi Ami?
Yes, but this was a רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, this was a
different ruling. Now the גמרא Gemara could have said it's a debate,
but the גמרא Gemara is going to try to reconcile the two
cases. Okay. You could have just said it's a debate, but let's
see what the answer is.
First case it's even a less
provable, right, you know, that he didn't do something with intention.
This was also he didn't do it with intention. He know he
did עיבוד, ibud, he just didn't do it לשמה. lishma. It was
the same לשמה lishma problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, now the
גמרא Gemara wants to say that they're reconcilable. So let's take a
look. ומאי שנא מדרבי אמי? U'mai shna mid'Rabbi Ami? How's it different
from Rabbi Ami? Why by Rabbi Ami did we split the— we
said you lose your fee and you're not believed? So the גמרא
Gemara says התם איכא למימר טעי בדרבי ירמיה. Hasam ika l'meimar ta'i
b'd'Rabbi Yirmiyah. No, because there you could have said that he was
making a mistake with the case of Rabbi Yirmiyah. What does it
mean?
Because maybe he, because Rabbi Yirmiyah said let him just lose the
fee for שם השם. Shem Hashem. So maybe he figured look, it's
the best of both worlds. I'll make this guy not lose out
his whole ספר תורה Sefer Torah and all I have to lose
out is being paid for the writing of the שם השם, Shem
Hashem, but I'm still going to get ninety-five percent of my fee.
So there he might have thought he was basically still going to
get paid. He was only going to lose out the fee for
writing שם השם. Shem Hashem. So therefore you don't have that basic
believability. Okay. אבל הכא כיון דקא מפסיד כולה, Aval hacha kivan d'ka
mafsid kula, since he knows that the whole ספר תורה Sefer Torah
is פסול, pasul, every single קלף klaf is פסול, pasul, so the
whole ספר תורה Sefer Torah is פסול. pasul. So he knows he's
going to מפסיד כולה אגריה, mafsid kula agrei, he'll lose all of
his שכר, sechar, all of his fee. ואתא ואמר, V'asa v'amar, and
he still nevertheless is coming forth and saying, אימר קושטא קאמר, eimar
kushta ka'amar, so clearly we have to presume that he is telling
the truth. Okay. So clearly here even if for technical reasons it's
not בידו, b'yado, all of,
circumstantially he clearly is telling the truth. Excellent. And now we are
caught up.